The golden spice, the powder handed down
from antiquity by the goddess Aphrodite
to soothe the ailing limbs of Odysseus's
sailors in the Iliad.
Well, none of that is true for multiple
reasons as history nerds are going to
point out, but it sounded good, didn't
it? The spice is turmeric, but we're
more interested in its main active
ingredient, curcumin, which had little
to do with the Greeks as it was used
further east. However, we have gone over
the clinical research on how curcumin
has arthritis benefiting effects. In
fact, we've gone over its pain relief
properties and how it improves joint
function in arthritis among other
benefits. And I thought to myself, well,
how exactly is it doing that? Are the
joints regenerating? Is Aphrodite
blowing kisses onto the boo-boo? What's
going on? So, I popped open a few
mechanistic studies to understand how
curcumin is fulfilling some of these
effects. And wouldn't you know it, it
actually does have some pretty profound
effects that specifically address some
major issues in arthritis, both
rheumatoid and osteoarthritis, but
focusing on osteoarthritis where the
joint structure is often compromised by
multiple things going wrong at once.
Like the degradation of collagen in the
cartilage that destabilizes the joint,
or the reduction in key cells that
maintain the health of the cartilage
called chondrocytes, or increased
inflammation that starts the whole
process off causing both previous
issues. The point being, arthritis has
many problems associated with it, and
yet curcumin seems to be able to address
many of them. For example, this one
datum shows us two clues.
You know how I mentioned that arthritis
is plagued with degradation of collagen?
Well, the main enzymes responsible for
that degradation are called
metalloproteinases
or MMPs. They get secreted by cells
called chondrocytes in your cartilage,
and they interact with mature collagen
structure and nibble away. So, returning
to this one graph,
these are values measuring the amount of
these proteins that are present. The
higher the vertical axis, the more of
these MMPs are present represented in
the white bars. And the horizontal axis
is varying concentrations of the golden
spice,
curcumin. So, we clearly see MMP
proteins are dramatically reduced when
exposed to any concentration of
curcumin. The main point here is that
one major aspect of arthritis joint
damage is punched in the mouth by
curcumin.
But, I did mention that there are two
clues out of this single graph, and we
did focus on the white bars, but there's
more here, the black bars.
We see increases in these proteins with
curcumin addition, and the protein is
collagen. So, that means that curcumin
encourages these chondrocytes to not
only produce less of the destructive
molecules, but more of the structural
proteins for the joint, collagen. Okay,
now we're seeing some ways by which
curcumin enacts its clinical benefits,
but there's one more thing that I want
to get to because it addresses another
concern related to arthritis, which is
the actual survival and maintenance of
these critical chondrocytes. If you're
interested in learning about the
inflammation aspects of curcumin
upstream of the MMPs and the collagen
production, which is a more involved
discussion, be sure to check out the
full analysis. It's
a much extended detailed video and
article that comes out for the Physionic
Insiders. Link to join is in the
description. And don't forget about all
these other benefits right here that you
could have as an Insider.
Up to now, we've been discussing these
proteins produced during arthritis, so
MMPs that degrade the structure of the
joint and the collagen that secures the
the and strengthens the joint. But, what
about the actual factory that produces
both of these proteins, the chondrocytes
themselves? Remember, I mentioned that
in osteoarthritis, you'll also get
reductions in these cells. So, what can
curcumin do for us there? Well, the
researchers also identified a protective
effect of curcumin on the chondrocytes
themselves. When the arthritic
environment was present, chondrocytes
were less able to multiply and
replenish. But, when curcumin was
present, the chondrocytes thrived. So,
this tells us a few different things.
One, that curcumin protects against
arthritis by reducing destructive
enzymes and encouraging collagen
maintenance. The second thing is that
these data alone are insufficient, but
paired with the clinical data, this
indicates curcumin has widespread
benefit in protecting against arthritis.
In fact, there are many different ways
that curcumin can alleviate arthritis,
and I cover a lot more right here,
including many special circumstances. I
hope that this was interesting follow-up
to the clinical data. Thanks for tuning
in, and I'll catch you soon again. Bye.